now let's go back to our cache
optimizations which are about reducing
the Amat we have seen that Amat can be
reduced by reducing the heat time and we
have seen several
techniques that do this the aat can also
be reduced by reducing the M rate and we
will now look at some techniques that
try to do that so in our work on
reducing the Miss rate we really need to
consider what are the causes of Misses
so what can cause misses and the causes
of Misses are what we call the Tre C's
you should remember this because very
often we will refer to the trees and you
need to know that the trees are
compulsory misses capacity misses and
conflict misses a compulsory Miss is a
miss that occurs when a block is
accessed for the first time it's called
compulsory because you have to have this
Miss so even if we have an INF inite
cash that starts out empty we would
still have the compulsory misses but we
would not have any of the other two
kinds so a compulsory Miss is a miss you
have to have simply because for the
first time you have to bring a block
into the cash capacity misses are misses
that we have on blocks that were in the
cach but were evicted because we didn't
have enough room in the cash because the
cash is of a finite size so these are
misses that we would not have in an
infinite cash but capacity misses would
be misses even in a fully associative
cache of the given size so for example
if we have an 8 kilobyte cache that is
let's say direct map we have a capacity
Miss if that block would not be found in
the cach even if it was fully
associative 8 kilobyte cache and finally
conflict misses occur because of
conflicts within a set so the block was
evicted not because the cash didn't have
enough space in it but because it had
limited
associativity so a conflict Miss is a
miss that would not be a Miss if the
cash was fully associative and of the
same size so now some of the obvious
techniques for reducing the Mis rate
will Target some of these so for example
a larger
cache would help us reduce the number of
capacity misses a larger associativity
would help us reduce the conflict misses
a better replacement policy would also
help us with conflict misses but all of
those techniques also affect the heat
time so now let's look at some
techniques that are trying to reduce the
Miss rate without necessarily increasing
the hit time in return